<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessitie and antiquitie of catechizing. By IF.</title>
            <author>I. F., fl. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853535</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00509)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessitie and antiquitie of catechizing. By IF.</title>
                  <author>I. F., fl. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by B. Alsop] for R. M[eighen],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In catechetical form.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18920:1"/>
            <p>THE NECESSITIE AND ANTIQVITIE OF <hi>CATECHIZING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY I. F.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PRO, Cap. 22. Ver. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Traine vp a Childe in the way hee ſhould goe, and when hee is olde, he will not depart from it.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted for R. M. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:18920:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>DEI VERITAS FILIA</p>
                  <p>VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VM DEI</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18920:2"/>
            <head>OF THE NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITIE AND ANTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing.</head>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>Queſtion I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is a Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>It is an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gien, which the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour teacheth the inferiour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>Queſteon 2.</head>
               <p>Whether is catechiſing neceſſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, for theſe two reaſons. Firſt, becauſe otherwiſe no man could cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know or worſhip GOD aright: Secondly, becauſe it is Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18920:3"/>
               <p>as hereafter it ſhall appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>Queſtion 3.</head>
               <p>Of what antiquitie is the doctrine and practiſe of catechiſing?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label>
               </p>
               <p>It is of great antiquitie, as it may appeare by a briete and orderly nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof in theſe thrée diſtinct times.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from the creation of the world vnto the dayes of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from Chriſt to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt time.</head>
               <div n="4" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 4.</head>
                  <p>WAs it practiſed from the Creation to Moſes?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, God inſtructed <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Adam</hi> and the religious Patriatres in the Church inſtructed
<pb facs="tcp:18920:3"/>their potterity from age to age.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 5.</head>
                  <p>Did God inſtruct Adam?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea, both before, and after his fall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 6.</head>
                  <p>Shew that God inſtructed Adam before his fall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may be the men two dayes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, by the particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions which he gave to <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 7.</head>
                  <p>By what reaſon can you ſhew that God inſtructed Adam before his fall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>By theſe two.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, as no man knoweth the thinges of man, ſaue the ſpirit of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is in him: euen ſo the thinges of God knoweth no man, but the ſpirite of God, <hi>1. Cor. 2.11.</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if God had not inſtructed <hi>Adam</hi> he could not haue knowne nor done the will of God.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18920:4"/>
                  <p>Secondly, where no Law is, there is no tranſgraſſion, <hi>Rom. 4.15.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore if God had not inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Adam,</hi> and giuen him lawes, hée could not haue ſinned; for ſinne is nothing el<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> but the tranſgreſſion of the Law, <hi>1. Iohn. 2.4.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 8.</head>
                  <p>What then bee the particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which God gaue to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam before his fall?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>They are diuers, and namely, theſe fiue.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that mankind ſhould bee multiplied in the holy eſtate of mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,<note place="margin">Matth. 9.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Gen. 2.24.</hi> therefore ſhall a man leaue his father and his mother, and ſhall cleaue to his wife, and they ſhal be one fleſh, and all other multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind out of the holy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of marriage, is ordinarily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſome iudgement of God.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that hee ſhould haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and dominion ouer the fiſhes of the Sea, and ouer the ſoules of the
<pb facs="tcp:18920:4"/>heauen, and ouer euery beat that moueth vpon the earth. <hi>Gen. 1.28.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that his meate ſhould bee the hearbes of the earth, and the fruit of the trées, <hi>Gen. 1.29.</hi> for man lineth not by bread onely, but by eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God, <hi>Matth. 4.4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, that he ſhould not liue i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ely, but dreſſe and keepe the garden of Eden. <hi>Gen. 2.15.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, that hee ſhould not eate of the fruite of the tree of knowledge of god and euill, vpon paine of death. <hi>Gen. 2.17.</hi> for in the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 9.</head>
                  <p>Shew me now alſo what inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions God gaue to Adam after his fall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>God gaue <hi>Adam</hi> theſe fiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions after his fall.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, he inſtructed <hi>Adam</hi> in the miſtery of redemption, <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> when God ſpeaking to that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent (called the Diuell and Sathan.
<pb facs="tcp:18920:5"/>Apoc. <hi>12.9.</hi>) ſayeth thus. <hi>I will put enmitie betweene thee and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and betweene thy ſeed and her ſeed, it ſhall breake thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele:</hi> when he ſayeth, it ſhall breake thy head, his meaneth the ſeede of the woman, that is, Chriſt, the ſeede of the Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> who at his firſt comming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queted Sathan, and deliuered the faithfull out of his thraldome. <hi>Hebrewes 2.14.</hi> For as much then as the children are partakers of fleſh and bloud, he alſo himſelfe like wiſe tooke part of the ſame, that through deatly he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the Deuill, and deliuer them, who through ſeare of death, wereall their life time ſubiect to bondage.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, he inſtructed <hi>Adam</hi> to offer ſacrifices, which were types and ſhadowes of the ſartifice of Chriſts body to be offced to make ſatiſfaction to God for the ſins of all the faith full.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he taught <hi>Adam</hi> that in offering of ſacrifices, hee muſt by
<pb facs="tcp:18920:5"/>faith apprehend Chriſt, who was ſhadowed and prefigured in thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cufices, or elſe he could not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God: whereupon it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi> that by faith <hi>Abell</hi> offered vnto God a more excellent ſacrifice then <hi>Cain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, he taught <hi>Adam,</hi> that thoſe were acceptable to God which beleeuedin the promiſed ſeede of the woman, that is, in Chriſt, who was to come, and that thoſe were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God which beleeued not in Chriſt to come, and ſo it was knowne euer ſince the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> that ſome beleeued in Chriſt, and mere ſaued, and ſome did not beleeue in Chriſt, and there ſore were reiected of God.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, when men beganne to bée multiplyed vpon the earth, the Lord forbade the faithfull to make maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the vnbelauers, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the teproofe of ſuch marriages <hi>Gen. 6.2.</hi> and this is confirmed in the new Teſtament, which diſagraeth not from the old. <hi>2. Cor. 6.14.</hi> Bee
<pb facs="tcp:18920:6"/>yee not vnequally yoked together with vnbeleeuers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 10.</head>
                  <p>Seeing theſe inſtructions giuen to Adam preſently after his fall, are fundamental points of true religion, and the fourth inſtruction is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the three former, declare the ſame more euidently, that it being better knowne, may make a deeper impreſſion in our mindes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may bee plainely declared foure wayes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by the examples of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Abell</hi> by faith was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> for his infidelity was reiected, <hi>1. Iohn. 3.12.</hi> for it was faith that made <hi>Abels</hi> worke, that is his ſacrifice accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi> and it was want of faith, that made <hi>Kaines</hi> worke, that is, his ſacrifice vnacceptable to God, becauſe without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb. 11.6.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the faithfull though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, are called the ſonnes of God,
<pb facs="tcp:18920:6"/>and the poſterity of vnbelécuers, are called the daughters of men. <hi>Geneſ. 6.2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, this difference of belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and vnbeleeuers, was typically ſhadowed out in the diſtinction of cleane and vncleane beaſts, <hi>Gen. 7.2.</hi> where <hi>Noah</hi> is commaunded to take into the Arke of euery cleane beaſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and of vnclean two. And a plain interpretation hereof wee haue, <hi>Act. 10.15.</hi> where the Lord forbiddeth <hi>Peter</hi> to count thoſe Gentiles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, whoſe hearts God had purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith, <hi>Acts. 15.9.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> there was no ſaluation to any but by faith in Chriſt; for all the promiſes of God are yea and Amen in Chriſt: <hi>2. Cor. 1.20.</hi> and therefore the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Patriarkes that liued before and after the flond, are commended, <hi>Heb. 11.5.</hi> and the vnbeleeuers of thoſe times are omitted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 11.</head>
                  <p>You haue ſhewed that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed Adam both before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:18920:7"/>his fall. ſhew me now that the faithfull haue inſtructed their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from age to age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may be ſhewed by an orderly rehearſall of ſome ſpecial faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from generation to generation.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Adam</hi> inſtructed his childri in the meſtery of redemption, other wiſe they could not haue offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice as they did, <hi>Gen. 4.3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly thoſe patriarkes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>Gen. 5.</hi> were Inſtructors of others, as the commendation of their faith. <hi>Heb. 11.5.</hi> may perſwade vs. And it is particularly written of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> in the Epiſtle of <hi>Iude,</hi> ver. <hi>14.</hi> and of <hi>Noah, 2. Pet. 2.5.</hi> that they mere teachers of others.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>Abraham</hi> inſtructed his family: for when <hi>Lor</hi> was taken and tarried away captiue, hee tooke out of his owne family <hi>318.</hi> perſons, which he had inſtructed in religion, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after the foure kings vnto <hi>Dan</hi> put them to flight, and brought again <hi>Lot, Gen. 14.14.</hi> Alſo the Lord min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:18920:7"/>to deſtroy <hi>Sodom</hi> reuealed his purpoſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſayd thus: <hi>Gen. 18.19.</hi> For I know him that he will commaund his children and his hou ſhold after him, that they kape the way of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the commendation of <hi>Lot, 2. Pet 2.7.</hi> Witneſſeth his rali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious care in this point.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, <hi>Iſaak</hi> was carefull for his ſonnes, that they ſhould be religious, and was grieued for the profanenes of <hi>Eſau. Gen. 26.35.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixthly, <hi>Iacob</hi> was religious him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and therefore carefull for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his children.</p>
                  <p>Seuenthly, <hi>Iob</hi> liuing in the daies of <hi>Iaakob,</hi> or neere that time, was carefull that his children ſhould feare God, as it appeareth, in that he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſatrifice for them whiles they were feaſting. <hi>Iob. 1.5.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eightly, and laſtly, when the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were trady to depart out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> the Lord commaunded them, that when their children ſhould aske them why they keepe the Paſſeouer
<pb facs="tcp:18920:8"/>yearely, they ſhould teach them the reaſon thereof. <hi>Exod. 12.26.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond time.</head>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 1.</head>
                  <p>You haue ſhewed that inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in religion was vſed from the creation to Moſes, ſhew mee now the continuance thereof from Moſes to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may be ſhewed two wayes: Firſt, by the commandement of God. Secondly, by the continuall practiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 2.</head>
                  <p>What commandement hath God giuen for inſtruction of youth?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>If may ſuffice to mention two.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is written, <hi>Deut. 6 6.</hi> All theſe words which I commaund thée this day ſhall bee in thine heart, and thou ſhalt rehearſe them continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnto thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou tarrieſt in thine
<pb facs="tcp:18920:8"/>houſe, &amp; as thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt down, and when thou riſeſt vp.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is written, <hi>Pſal. 78. v. 5</hi> Heeſtabliſhed a teſtimony in <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and appointed a law in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which be commaunden out Fathers, that they ſhould make them knowne to their children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſe 6.</hi> That the generation to come might know them, sucn the children which ſhould be horne, who ſhould ariſe and declare them to theyr children. <hi>Verſe 7.</hi> That they might ſet their hope in God, art net forget the workes of God, but kéepe his commandemen's.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 3.</head>
                  <p>Shew mee alſo the continuall practiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may bee ſhewed by theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples following.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the Captaine and gouernour of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſayth thus, I and mine houſe wilſerue the Lord, <hi>Ioſhua 24.15.</hi> profeſſing both for himſelfe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18920:9"/>alſo for his Familie, that they will ſerue the Lord, though others decline and fall a way.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, King <hi>Dauid</hi> inſtructed <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne, as <hi>Salomon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>Prou. 4.3.</hi> for I was my Fathers Sonne, tender and deare in the ſight of my mother, when he taught mée and ſayde vnto me: Let thine heart hold faſt my wordes, koope my commaundements, and thou ſhalt liue, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Alſo <hi>Dauid</hi> prouided that his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were inſtructed by others beſides himſelfe, for it is thus written, <hi>1 Chr. 37.32. Iehiel</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hachmony</hi> mas with the Kings ſonnes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Queene <hi>Bathſheba</hi> the mother of <hi>Salomon,</hi> admoniſhed her ſonne of thrée thinges, as <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, <hi>Prou. 32.2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, that hee ſhould not giue his ſtrength to women, <hi>ver. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, that hee ſhould not giu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelfe to drinke wine, <hi>ver. 4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that he ſhould defend the afflicted, and the poore, <hi>ver. 8.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18920:9"/>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Salomon</hi> inſtructed his children, as it appeareth, <hi>Prou, 4. verſ. 1:</hi> Heare yée children the inſtruction of a Father, and attend to know vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>ver. 2.</hi> for I giue you good doctrine, forſake you not my Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver. 10.</hi> Heare D my Sonne, and receyue my ſayings, and the years of thy life ſhall be many.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver. 11.</hi> I haue taught thée in the way of wiſdome, I haue ledde thee in right pathes, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, <hi>Obadiah</hi> the Gouernour of <hi>Ababs</hi> houſe, ſayth thus to <hi>Eliah: 1. King. 18.12.</hi> But I thy ſeruant feare the Lord from my youth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is euident, that he was inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his younger yeares.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his fourth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooke, and eight Chapter of antiquity and his ſecond booke againſt <hi>Appion,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat the children of the Iewes could <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſwere as readily to euery point of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Law, as to their owne names.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18920:10"/>
               <head>The third time.</head>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 1.</head>
                  <p>YOu haue ſhewde the continuall practiſe of catechiſing or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the younger ſort from the creation to Moſes, and from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to Chriſt, ſhew me now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance thereof vnder the Goſpell from Chriſt to this preſent day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This may bee ſhewed thrée wayes</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by reaſons grounded vpper Scripture.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, by the commandement of God.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, by ſome examples.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 2.</head>
                  <p>What be the reaſons which proue the continuance thereof vnder the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>They are fine.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the thrée reaſons renderen
<pb facs="tcp:18920:10"/>
                     <hi>Pſal, 78.</hi> Why youth ſhould bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed vnder the Law, holde alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that the generations to come might know the commandements of God, <hi>Pſal. 78.6.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, that the generations to come might declare the ſame to theyr children, <hi>Pſal. 78.6.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that all generations to come might ſet their hope on God. <hi>Pſ. 78, 7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the inſtruction of youth is part of the morall law, euen of the fift commandement, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth vnder the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the couenant betweena God and his Church (which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, <hi>Eſai 54.10. Ierem. 32.32, &amp; 33.20.</hi>) cannot continue, except youth be inſtructed.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is continued vnder the Goſpell, and therefore the inſtruction of youth is continued.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, there is vnder the Goſpel as well milke, that is, the firſt principles
<pb facs="tcp:18920:11"/>of religion, giuen to yong Chriſtians as ſtronger meate to the elder ſor<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> according to the Apoſtles ſpéech an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> practiſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.15. 2. Pet. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>1. Cor. 3.2.</hi> I haue fedde yo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with milke, and not with ſtronge meate, for you were not hitherto a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to be are it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 3.</head>
                  <p>What commandement then ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God giuen in the new Teſtament?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two commandements ſpecially.</p>
                  <p>The friſt is <hi>Eph<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ. 6.4.</hi> And yée fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prenoke not your children <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wrath, but bring them vp in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and information of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, <hi>Galat. 6.6.</hi> Let him that is taught in the word, communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to him that teacheth in all goo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="question">
                  <head>Queſtion 4.</head>
                  <p>What examples can you alledge</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> preache<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> repentance, <hi>Matth. 3.2.</hi> and fait<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Chriſt, <hi>Acts. 29.4.</hi> and alſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18920:11"/>baptized young Chriſtians, <hi>Matth. 3.6.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Chriſt preached the ſame doctrine, ſaying <hi>Mark. 1.15.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and beleeue the Goſpell. Alſo he baptized. <hi>Iohn 3.22.</hi> By his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <hi>Iohn 4.2.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly the twelue Apoſtles were commaunded to preach the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Matth. 10.7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the ſeuenty Diſciples were alſo commaunded to preach the ſame Doctrine <hi>Luk: 10.9.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, <hi>Peter</hi> preached the ſame doctrine and baptized, <hi>Act. 2.3.8.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixtly, <hi>Philip</hi> preached to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans, and baptized them. <hi>Act. 8. verſ. 5.12.</hi> Alſo her inſtructed and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized the Eunuch, <hi>Act. 8.26.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seuenthly, <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Philippi</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and baptized both <hi>Lydia, Act. 26.14.</hi> And alſo the Kéeper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priſon, <hi>Act. 16.30.</hi> And at <hi>Corinthus,</hi> hee baptized <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Cains: 2. Cor. 1.14.</hi> and the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus, 1. Cor. 1.16.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eightly, <hi>Timotheus</hi> was caterhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb facs="tcp:18920:12"/>by his mother <hi>Eunice,</hi> &amp; by <hi>Lois</hi> his Grandmother, <hi>1. Tim. 2.5.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ninthly, the principall heades of the Chriſtian Catechizing, ſet down <hi>Heb. 6.2.</hi> Witneſſe the pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctiſe of catechizing in al churches, and may ſerue in ſtead of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
